Did you learn calculus and then get G a or did you cheat and get the a like it's like you know the answer
Yeah, you're right. The a isn't the goal. It's the representation of your knowledge and your mastery
This is Michael Seibel with Dalton called well today. We're going to talk about setting goals
More specifically all of the pitfalls involved in setting or trying to accomplish goals
That's sort of founders. We work with 10 to fall for
Dalton, why don't you set this one up? Yeah, you know when we were talking about it this morning the the
phrase or the meme that came to mind was the one
Play stupid games when stupid prizes
You know and again what I think it means in this context is if if you set goals or if you start playing one specific game
That is silly to begin with or that hat that's like clearly a bad call
Yeah, the prizes the implications of that the things that you win are going to be equally silly or
Non-sensical or non-productive, okay, and so we see a lot of people
Who set goals to in effect play play kind of stupid games? Let's talk about the stupid games
And then we'll talk about the stupid prizes at the end. Those are those are maybe even more fun
So you know, I think it's it makes sense to split this up into
Mistakes that people make setting goals, and then mistakes people make trying to accomplish these goals
So I would say like the first one
And maybe I'll start with the simplest is when people set goals that are so aggressive they aren't motivational
And they're basically missing the understanding of what the purpose of setting a goal is right like you want to motivate yourself to
Act smarter faster more intelligently than you would otherwise
And often them people are setting goals that are too aggressive
Because they're motivated by fear you know in YC we see this all the time and what's an example of a too aggressive goal?
Like what do you think I can give you an example?
Oh, yeah, you know
I'll see a YC founder who comes in to YC just starting to build their product and
They tell me by demoday we want to have you know 30k an emerald and
And we want to do that because some alum told us that like that's how much emerald you need in order to raise money on demoday and it's just like
How many errors can be set in three sentences?
What's an example comes to your mind my most common example is someone
That believes once they launch a product it will immediately succeed and take off and so it's like we're gonna spend three months building this app
We're going to put it in the app store. We're gonna launch and
Then we're gonna get a hundred thousand D you yeah, yeah, it's yeah, like two weeks later
Yeah, it's always the plan is they're gonna put it out and then it's gonna immediately take off those are always the goals
that
That are rough and what's funny is we're always like why do you launch sooner?
So you have more time to make a grow after a launch is like no, no, no
We're gonna spend all the time making it good
And so they want to lose it's gonna immediately take off top the app starts a hundred percent
Why would we launch something bad then it won't take off Dalton? Jesus. Yeah, we we we we we're gonna talk to some influencers
You know, we're gonna do a social media launch. We've got it all lined up. We're have a wait list. So yeah top of the charts definitely
game on so
Both examples of being too aggressive
I'm the next one that comes up a lot is fake metrics
And we've talked about this a little bit
But you know for companies who
Charged their customers money somehow creating a goal incremented in something that's not money
Hey, my product cost $10 a month, but I'm measuring registered users
I want to hit you know a thousand registered users and it's like
That's weird like hell if users is gonna be the metric like why wouldn't it be active users, right?
Like just like if we're gonna be in that world. Well, that's too hard Michael. That's why fair
But if we're charging them, why wouldn't it be the amount of money we make like that seems even simpler
But I think you've seen a wide variety of fake metrics that goes way further than users, right?
Yeah
Okay, county and hits on your website. That's an oldie but a goodie
Yeah, yes, yes, counting downloads, but not registrations is a good one. Yeah
counting users as people
That started the registration process and didn't finish it
counting users as people that downloaded your product opened it closed it after five seconds and never open it again as users
We've heard that one
Just basically like a thousand and one different ways to avoid
the actual
Meaning of the metric which is to capture if it's working or not
You know it's like every every which way people are so creative in finding ways to like
Not actually measure the thing that they know they're supposed to be measuring and I can ever tell if they're doing it to
fool themselves or to fool like investors or authority you I'm saying like it's hard for me to tell when someone is practicing
Self-disruption that like number of downloads is the right metric or if they think that no one else realizes that that's obviously
Like no one can tell what they're trying to do we can tell and honestly it's probably both right? It's probably a combination of both right like
Um, okay, so here's another one that I see a lot especially with fundraising stupid comparatives so like
in 2021
Tiger gave this company a hundred million dollar funding when they accomplished blank
500,000 of ARR
therefore
We will be able to raise a hundred million dollars of funding when we accomplish
500,000 ARR right Michael right like there's no difference between you know
Summer 2022 and summer 2021
At all and that's how it works right is investors what they do is they just
Are always consistent and they always
Same decisions and it's easy for you to tell reading the tech crunch announcement. Why the investor made the investment
Right, it's clear like I read the article
Um, you know this VCE invested in this company were kind of like that company in some superficial ways
It's in the bag we got it
And then the other one that I love about it is like no Michael like that round was announced last week
That just happened
it's like
sorry, but
Lots of things are announced way after they happen
And so again, well, I think what we're saying about what's the stupid goal in this case
Playing the stupid game here is trying to create superficial resemblance to other things
Yes as opposed to deep
The thing is working or maybe there's a deeper analog to the other thing
But if you're just focusing on the very surface level stuff
Yeah, you're that is not a smart game to be playing
One other example maybe an old one we talked about in the past, you know with Facebook where you might be able to argue
Well, they raised money when they only had a small number of users right and then you completely punt on the fact that like
That small number of users were 95% 2 hour a day Facebook users. Yes. So it was like the engagement was like
incredible
Yeah, if you can replicate Facebook's engagement
Then you've got something versus replicating. I don't know. It's for college kids or I don't know people have very superficial
um
Stuff there. Oh god. You brought up one um on our list about sandbagging. Let's talk about sandbagging a little bit
Yeah, so sandbagging. I don't know how much people are used to that term um, I think it's
I think I it's a golf term
But sandbagging is basically where you set goals that are intentionally way easy to hit
With the goal of blowing them out of the water, right? So say you know you can accomplish something in one week
The sandbag version of the goal is to get yourself a month and then when you go around and you hit the goal
You like look like a genius and what's funny is when you are working for the man
When you're working at a company like office space, you know, you're in a cube farm somewhere
Um
It makes sense to sandbag goals and that's actually great career advice. I suppose is that you you know
You set really you convince people that something is really hard to do and then you see their expectations
What a great way to get promoted or whatever
Of course, whoever there's a problem
If you're used to doing that and that's how you think all things should work
When you start working for yourself when you were your own boss
You are screwing yourself
And what maybe a good strategy to like rest invest working at Google or Facebook and to just do his little work as possible
By sandbagging goals and working three hours a week or whatever people do
When you're the boss
Do you see how that's like
Not great
Well, and you better believe that big company you work for didn't have that culture when it was starting
Yeah, the founders of that company. We're not doing that. No, all right. Let's talk about accomplishing
goals, so okay, let's say I set a good goal right I
I'm a post launch b2b SaaS company with a couple users and I am
Setting a goal of getting my first 10 paying users right great like we're in the right ballpark
Let's hear about how people screw up
Accomplishing goals and somehow kind of still play the stupid game
Right out of the gate. It's the way that you accomplished it is something that you know in your heart is not
like
What's the word? I want to use kosher. I don't know. What would what would you use a Michael like?
um
I like using the word cheating like you know, it's like
You're taking a calculus test
Did you learn calculus and then get d a or did you cheat and get the a like it's like you know the answer to that question
Yeah, you're right. The a
Isn't the goal. It's the representation of your knowledge and your mastery
If you didn't
Learn something when accomplishing the goal
Maybe you didn't accomplish the goal. You know, you can fool investors. You can fool co-found
You can fool while he's yeah, people
Are very trusting and so I think the way
The mistake people make is they think that because they fooled people in a short term
They won't know they didn't hit the goal
There like yeah, you know what I actually did was I got my friends and family to do probable or what I act
You know, there's like something and where you're like yeah, this didn't
Which you but no one else can be aware of us. You're like well, I guess
I guess this worked. I guess this is how this goes
So another way that people screw up the accomplishing goals is not understanding how to take the L
Okay, maybe you set the wrong goal and instead of um
Realizing that and setting a new goal
You cheat or do you want to these other tactics to try to accomplish it because you feel as though
Not accomplishing your goal as a failure in of itself
Man, I find founders screw this up
constantly. It's like
You don't have to assume you're going to be good at setting goals
Like you can give yourself some slack. Assume you're going to be bad at it and like
You can adjust over time. You can set better goals over time. You can not accomplish your goals and learn from it
um
There isn't this you know sometimes in YC. I think people feel this like oh
We're grading them on whether they accomplished their goals and it's like first of all
We're not grading. We're not your teacher. We're not your boss and second of all like
Your job is to work on the hardest problem your company like that like if you've made progress on the hardest problems in your company
You're doing well
Like that's the that's the whole gist of this. It's not like oh, did you like
Release that feature when you said you were going to you know that no one's gonna use
Oh, man, and then you talk about excuses a lot. How do how do people screw that up when they don't accomplish their goal?
I just noticed a lot that when folks set goals and are able to hit them
That's okay
But when folks are in a position where they really think it's important to make a lot of excuses on why it's not their fault
And everyone else's fault and they just have this like inner desire
To like tell me all the excuses. I think that's not hopeful in that like again
I'm not the bot like I don't care. Okay, you didn't hear go great. Let's move on like like like it
It's like they want redemption
And so I just think that it's good
If something doesn't work to accept it to acknowledge it to look at it
But realize you're the boss of yourself and you should just
Not feel in need to make a million excuses or have like like create this long narrative where you're the victim and everyone else
It's not your fault and your heart was in the right place and you did everything right but everyone else was wrong
This is usually stuff about sales cycle
Well, you know the sales cycle is just long like this is just too hard and it's just when people do this
My message to them is like hey, that's fine. I'm not saying your excuses wrong
But like why are you spending all this energy trying to plead a case like you're in court
That the thing didn't work as opposed to like well move on and make something that does work. How about that
spend energy in a positive proactive direction then
Weave in the narrative of yourself is the person who did great, but you're misunderstood by the universe
This is an internal tool like this is a tool for you to use your help yourself. This is not
A tool for you to please someone else like that. That's kind of a relevant
So let's do the takeaway here. You know you set this up with play stupid games win stupid prizes
Um, let's talk about some of the stupid prizes that we see companies with
Where do you want to start?
If you set that goal
If you start playing a silly game
You can win at the game. We see lots of people win at the game and so one of the game one of those stupid games
Sometimes people play is just how much money can I raise the more money I raise the better my goal is most dollars raised
And the bigger that number is the better I am. So you're playing the game you won the game. Congratulations
What's the prize you win Michael? What's the stupid prize if you play the race as much as you can game
Often you lose control of your company
So like when you confront the challenges suddenly, you know your board can fire you
Often you find yourself burning tons of money because all people who gave you money expect you to spend it
Um, oftentimes you have the wrong people on your team
You've a bunch of people who think you've made it who think that this is you know the next Google when a reality
It's it's it's not
um
And then last
You might have to change what you're working on or change the problem or pivot in some significant way
But now they're all of these people and all this money and all this momentum going down a direction
That's driving your company off the cliff and that pivot becomes 10 times harder or or damn near impossible oftentimes
Um
But you did win the fundraising game. Yeah, it's a congratulations. So congratulations
More than fundraising game here's your prize
You have a messed up company that shouldn't have raised all the money and you've got to dig yourself out of a disaster
And everyone's mad at you. Here you go. You won the prize. Have fun
The next fun one is
I want to feel like someone running a big company. I want to have 15 employees. I want to have 100 employees
I want to have 500 employees. I want to be a boss of a lot of
That's just a number of employees. I want a real big team. I want to move real fast. That's my game. Yeah
It's always about moving fast. That's the lies like if we had this we could finally move as fast as like
You know, we could finally build all the things that I want us to build
So what's this stupid prize on that one Dalton? Now you wake up one day and you look at the spreadsheet of your burn
And you you look at all the people that work at your company and you're like oh no
And get what it's now your problem
Because now you might have to do a layoff you might have to let people go
You might mess up people's lives that believed in you
You might
Mess up that or have moral issues there
It's like the worst thing ever to over hire and have to deal with it
And if you talk to someone that's had to deal with this
This is usually one of the more the biggest failures if you look at your life
I know that's how I feel like personally is the biggest failures I've ever had
We're definitely having to let people go that I shouldn't have hired
So congratulations. You win the prize. You will hire a bunch of people. You're a big important person
Now you're responsible for all of this
Yes, yes
Um, here's the other one. I love this one um
Dalton I need an executive team
It's it's time for my company to become a real serious company and to do that. I need an executive team
And so I'm going to spend the next year recruiting the executive team like it's time. I'm ready to grow up Dalton
I'm ready to grow up
What do you think about this one? How many great executives have we encountered over the year?
I mean
Look
I think if all you do is consume like VC content you're this is something idea that gets
engaged in your brain and I think maybe there is a time where this is a good answer
But it's like so much of the the VC content is aimed at late stage founders, which is pretty weird
Um, it's like putting out content that's like you know
How to care for your um
Your Ferrari or something like like again. I don't really know who a lot of this
The majority of the people that consume it are like two or three person startups
And if you
If all of your advice is like hire an executive team and you have like a three-person
Pre-PMF startup like oh man, like you can get someone to leave
You can get someone with a title to leave Google or Facebook or somewhere really impressive
And you think you're like a big winner that you got someone from this cool company to join your company
But then you wake up and you're like wow. What did I do? Like what usually happens is they either
Are either they join your startup because they they weren't doing well
I'm trying to give a nice way to say it either there's a reason they joined your startup and left Google
Or they had expectations that you were farther or along or more successful than you actually are and they get very upset with you
When they realize that your startup sucks
tricky
All right, the next one the next gift
That you receive when you play a stupid game. We've touched on this a little bit is
I'm now burning tons of money because I just scaled negative margins
You know, I had something that wasn't working in this city and I expanded that thing to 30 other cities
And now it's not working at a massive scale
And I did it because my investors told me to
And now those investors aren't taking my phone call and this is like so hard because I think people don't realize that either
Some stage of investors or at some point in your companies someone's going to pull out your finances and do basic arithmetic and ask themselves
Is this real
And like eventually you will be judged based on like is this real and sustainable
And if it's not like you know, hey sometimes you even get post IPO
Oh my life at some point
Those people are having a bad time. We're not going to name any name
It's not being post IPO and then having your stock with 95% of its value
I don't think not fun those people are having a good they play it a game and here's like the prize they have is
Is having a rough time? So I definitely feel as though
Founders make this mistake of like if I raise the last round by my massively scaling my negative margins
I'll be able to raise the next round and
That luck runs out at some point
You know the next topic is on you know acquiring companies and and I think that um
This comes in a number of flavors one is once again. We're finally grown up
We can make our first acquisition or like we want to get good at this acquisition things
So we got to start doing it. There's a lot of talent out there Michael and some really talented
Failing startups would love to be a be acquired by us and this will help us grow faster
So we're gonna we're gonna acquire them and by the way that doesn't mean that like
acquiring companies is
Bad it it just often means the folks who are thinking about it in startup land tend to be thinking about it too early
Is this is like another example of like taking later stage advice too early
When like the advice you should be taking is make your core business work like just make a core business
If you don't have product market for yourself
Probably not agree
You're laughing but people are probably like wait really? Yeah, really
You know I
Belt and I uh you're right. I am laughing because that's like that's an inconceivable concept in my mind like
Well, we're pre-product market fit. We should definitely be spinning up core dev
Here's another one that's in the news more and more lately um defrauding your customers selling your customer something and telling them it's one thing and
You know, it's not that thing and your customers lose money or your customers
Are in some way extremely harmed. What's the prize for doing that Dalton? Um no joke. It seems like there's people
Going to jail and getting arrested and people whose actual lives
Are now irrepably harmed by the games that they were playing to get growth or to get money and
Yeah, they're gonna spend you know best case scenario is spending years and years and years in court
And then the court system and just having your life
Changed like this isn't making a mistake. We're really clear here like your state of mind is is is is extremely important here
This is like knowingly pursuing a strategy
That you know as harming your users like
and and um
I think what's tricky is that oftentimes
People don't think this is happening
I think sometimes people forget that they're not playing a game
And I think especially in coven land. I don't know like one of my explanations is if you spend all day
On Twitter and discord and everything's a game and everything to joke or everything silly
You can kind of I just have noticed some folks lose themselves and not
Realize that the numbers in the spreadsheet are real dollars and I don't know
It's like we're not playing monopoly. We're not playing sellers at time
And I think that this the the prize that you win is the knock on the door
um
From the police
And that's when you're like oh wow this is this was real life and the last one our list
um
Playing the game of using your position as a startup founder to become an amazing investor
And and I think this one's like really tricky because
For one thing you definitely see a lot of famous startup founders have written kind of angel and checks in the companies that that
tend to do well
And so I think sometimes people confuse that
For oh, I should be spending a significant amount of my time
Looking around and trying to be an angel investor instead of making my company work and
I think that what if I can try to explain to you what's actually happening
When you're a good founder
Oftentimes you know other good people
And the opportunity you have to give them money requires almost no time or effort
And so you just and and like if you're a good founder oftentimes people are are offering you
To deals and so like you know you're spending five minutes saying yes
This is an obviously good thing. I use it or this is my friend. I want to support them
And the amount of time and effort you're spending writing these angel checks is basically nil
Like you know, I remember when I was
Starting social cam. I emailed Brian Chesky saying do you want angel invest? He was like sure
That's it like that was like that was the entire time that he spent probably less than 15 seconds
um
I think people don't see this so they think oh
I need to copy what I see investors on twitter doing. I need to go network
I need to go meet founders and
Advise them and do office hours and like all these things and it's like oh like classic example of cargo culting
Right like not really understanding what's going on the stupid game your plane is the status game
Like if you play status games where what you want to do is level up you want to
Put angel investor in your twitter bio or something
Okay, your plane is status game fair enough
The prices that you win playing the game is congratulations
Now a bunch of your money is tied up in ill-equid investments. The may or may not show up
So now maybe you're like financially strapped
Maybe you're worried about other stuff. You're worried about your startup
So maybe you're performing worse because your money is tied up somewhere
You have spent a bunch of time and stuff. You've totally pissed off your employees whether or not they would say it to your face
That is not a great way to win awards with your team
Yeah, you're a seinster. Congratulations. Yeah, so I think to wrap this up right
Sometimes
founders don't think enough about the bad consequences of the games they're playing
And once they really do the whole logic tree down to the end they'll realize that maybe
It's not worth playing those games and you might as well just build a good business
And even if that's a tricky message for you to internalize
Think about what you're teaching your team if you're making these mistakes right like they will copy
What you're doing because you define success in your company and so even if you're like oh for me
This is cool right like you know
For example if if becoming a status seeking angel investor is like what seems cool in your company
People in your company you start trying to do it instead of doing their work and so if they see a bunch number make sure
Yeah, people in the company start doing it. They's like it's kind of like a little bit
You know we're both parents. It's kind of like hey like if you don't want your kid to be a screw up
You don't do screw up shit in front of them like it's like a pretty simple like
one to one year
um and
On the flip side to kind of end with a positive note some of our best companies get so good
At goal setting and accomplishing goals that they
They move faster than we would ever imagine possible
Like they are just machines at doing this well and
I would argue that most people don't start doing this well
Most people who focus on setting goals and accomplishing them get better at it over time
But man the rate of improvement is sometimes shocking
You know sometimes their founders were kind of fooling themselves who are thinking like hey
I'm smart so I can coast on this stuff and it's like
Man outliers are smart and great executors and great trainers, right?
Like they have multiple things. They're great at they don't sandbag themselves
Any of the thoughts here Dalton I think we're good. I think it's well said. Thanks, man. Awesome. Thank you later